{
  "reference_number": "9192",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "After nine years of total inaction on climate change it is urgent that the current government sets some binding legislation in order to\n insure a path to emissions reduction among other environmental issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We must set ambitious (but achievable) goals, in order to set an example for other OECD countries in the Paris Agreement but also as\n\n a matter of urgency regarding the education and awareness of the NZ population- by setting clear goals as a country Kiwi's will be\n encouraged to examine areas of their own life in which they are negatively contributing to our current environmental crisis. NZ has\n\n the opportunity to become a world leader environmentally and setting this target would not only stay in line with the Paris agreement\n but it will help centre environmental issues, but it will emphasise the importance of climate change and government alongside\n traditional 'jobs and growth' concerns."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "There are many foreseeable problems with allowing the purchasing of international emissions reductions, and it should be avoided at\n\n all costs as NZ is an OECD country with the ability and resources to achieve a carbon zero target on it's own."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Presumably the only circumstance in which the bill would be revised would be in order to soften targets. There is argument regarding\n whether or not adhering to the Paris Agreement will in fact successfully mitigate climate change temperature rises to only 2 degrees-\n\n above which resulting sea level rise, ecosystem damage, and weather conditions are considered to be largely catastrophic and\n unknown. We cannot take risks beyond what has been budgeted for by the Paris Agreement."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Five years is a good interval as it will not run in line with the election cycle."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "See no. 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Assuming that each government carefully plans for and takes advice from appropriate sources to formulate action second budgets\nshould not need to be altered. As part of climate change mitigation planning government should be prepared for the increased\n\nlikelihood of natural disasters and there should be strategy in place to deal with shocks and stresses that are likely to effect our ability\nto meet emissions budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should also being a guideline regarding the wellbeing of people and place, including consideration of inter-generational equity\nand environmental justice."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be strong frameworks in place to ensure that planning for and the implementation of actions required to meet budgets\ncontinue regardless of who is in government."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "- Social, economic, and environmental equity for all New Zealanders and our natural environment. - Transition to low carbon\n\ntransportation networks - Supporting the agriculture industry to transfer to a low GHG future - Community engagement and education\n- Investment in low carbon industries- job creation"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Minus international emission reduction advice. The climate change commission should also monitor and advise of social issues\n\narising from low carbon transitions, climate change and community mindset and education"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Community engagement, communications and EDUCATION"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are already locked in for at least 1.5 degrees of climate change, it would be remiss to not include adaptation in the bill as disaster/\nemergency planning, infrastructure safeguards/ repairs and healthcare many other factors are likely to cost NZ a lot of money as a\n\nhighly coastal country. There in fact a lot of ground to catch up on after nine years of underfunded public sectors across the board."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Risk assessments need to be ongoing as science and probably futures change."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The more information accessible to the government regarding economic, environmental and social vulnerabilities brought about by\n\nclimate change the better prepared the country will be to adapt to and mitigate shocks and stresses."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is a relief to finally see some tangible action being taken by government on this issue! NZ contribute a very small proportion of\nglobal emissions but that does not in anyway excuse us from action, especially considering our high per capita emissions and\nemissions that are likely incurred offshore in relation to our own consumption. It is time NZ lays out a pathway to a positive and\n\nenvironmental regenerative future to work towards and ensure the future liveability of our country and planet."
    }
  ]
}
